<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse for a king and Parliament in four sections. Demonstrating I. The inconsistency of a free-state with the scituation of this countrey, and constitution of the people. II. Mischiefs incident to the continuance of their endeavours that act in order thereunto. III. The advantages probably attending a composure with the King of Scots. IV. Resolves to the grand objections that seeme to obstruct it. By a moderate and serious pen.</title>
            <author>W. C.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C151</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1021_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895396</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895396</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152860</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152860)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2328:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse for a king and Parliament in four sections. Demonstrating I. The inconsistency of a free-state with the scituation of this countrey, and constitution of the people. II. Mischiefs incident to the continuance of their endeavours that act in order thereunto. III. The advantages probably attending a composure with the King of Scots. IV. Resolves to the grand objections that seeme to obstruct it. By a moderate and serious pen.</title>
                  <author>W. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for G. Bedell and T. Collins, and are to be sold at their shop at the middle-Temple-gate in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: W.C.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "April. 26.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Monarchy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Constitution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152860:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE FOR A KING AND Parliament:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In four Sections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Demonſtrating
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>The inconſiſtency of a Free-ſtate with the ſcituation of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and conſtitution of the people.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>Miſchiefs incident to the continuance of their endeavours that act in order thereunto.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>III. <hi>The advantages probably attending a compoſure with the King of Scots.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>IV. <hi>Reſolves to the Grand Objections that ſeeme to obſtruct it.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By a moderate and ſerious Pen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bono ſervire Principi optima libertas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>G. Bedell</hi> and <hi>T. Collins,</hi> and are to be ſold at their ſhop at the middle-<hi>Temple</hi>-gate in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152860:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152860:2"/>
            <head>To Sir <hi>A.H.</hi> and thoſe ſpirits that pretend to <hi>Liberty</hi> in <hi>Democracy.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Deſign <hi>Liberty;</hi> not the <hi>name,</hi> but the <hi>thing;</hi> I aſſert not that which ſome Divines call <hi>Monarchy,</hi> but <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> as it relates to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> not that of the <hi>Jews;</hi> not in order to the Greatneſſe of a <hi>ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> but to the happineſſe of the <hi>whole peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> That Regal Politick Government, to whoſe protection I am entitled by my <hi>birth,</hi> for the preſervation of my freedome in <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>eſtate,</hi> and that, with <hi>more</hi> aſſurance than poſſibly can be ſecur'd under the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the <hi>many</hi> who often call that <hi>juſtice,</hi> and without remedy, which in truth is <hi>Faction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Next, I abhorre <hi>bloodſhed,</hi> and deeme one party in all <hi>warres</hi> guilty of <hi>murder;</hi> a crime
<pb facs="tcp:152860:3"/>which as it cries high for <hi>vengeance,</hi> ſo it cries loud for <hi>peaee,</hi> which he only endeavours that that acts <hi>no injury;</hi> I recommend this to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance you in the <hi>way to Peace,</hi> leſt you <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot</hi> us into the field of <hi>blood;</hi> perhaps your <hi>own</hi> as well as <hi>ours;</hi> for though you <hi>Vote</hi> at <hi>eaſe</hi> upon the hazard of our <hi>bodies,</hi> yet poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly in time, the <hi>evil</hi> may happen upon the <hi>Artiſt.</hi> If but <hi>one of you</hi> I convert, I have a full reward; for perhaps I may ſave a <hi>ſoule;</hi> however as the text ſpeaks, <hi>I ſhall hide a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of ſins.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in the way of Truth and Peace, <hi>W. C.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <div type="introduction">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152860:3"/>
               <head>THE Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>UR affairs labouring under variety of</hi> facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>nothing ſeems more rational to effect a due Compoſure, than the advice of the</hi> whole People; <hi>for that</hi> which binds all, ought by all to be debated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now, though the Parliament upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention is not ſo</hi> regular <hi>as may admit of no exception, yet ſince the</hi> whole people <hi>are not capable to be</hi> perſonally <hi>in Counſel, and that with reſpect to our fundamentals this way of Election has the</hi> repute <hi>to be the Repreſentative of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and that with reſpect to the</hi> preſent, <hi>it is not poſſible to have an Aſſembly nearer the foundation, and more paſsable to give forth the ſence of the people; Therefore as it were an high inſolence in any</hi> few <hi>to impoſe a Government upon the</hi> whole; <hi>ſo will it argue a strange inquietude of ſpirit, if ſingle perſons ſhall not acquieſce in the</hi> free major Vote <hi>of their judgements that ſhall be ſo aſsembled; for though in truth the</hi> major Vote <hi>may be the worſe, yet becomes it not a ſingle perſon ſo to judge; for thereof the conſequence will be, that every mans ſingle judgement ſhall be the rule of his obedience, which needs muſt engage us as to</hi> confuſion <hi>upon the</hi> variety <hi>of judgements that will happen, ſo to</hi> war <hi>for the laſt deciſion of the matters controverted, perſons of ſuch opinions being not capable to be over-rul'd by any other judicature.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152860:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Though therefore it becomes ſober men to acquieſce in their determinations, yet may it become all men that are</hi> concerned in the Reſult, <hi>to contribute their aſſiſtance in the</hi> way; <hi>That things being at full diſcuſt, and laid open according to truth, thereof they might be enabled to give a more ſound judgment. Upon this account, have I preſum'd to the</hi> publick, <hi>without the leaſt reflection upon</hi> paſt <hi>miſcarriages, to enquire conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the preſent ſtate of our affairs,</hi> What ſettlement may beſt conduce to our happineſſe in the future; <hi>wherein I know not how I can deſign to my ſelf any other intereſt than</hi> Peace, <hi>for though I have hapned to diſpleaſe</hi> one <hi>party, yet I never actually oblig'd the</hi> other, <hi>and do ſecure my ſelf no laſting comfort upon earth but in the Union of</hi> Both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now after a ſad revolve I find my ſelf confined in this ſence. That,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I. <hi>That which we call a Free-ſtate, is inconſiſtent with the</hi> ſcitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of this Countrey, and conſtitution of the people.</head>
               <p>I Deſign only to inforce, <hi>plain,</hi> ſenſible and <hi>modern</hi> arguments, as a word in <hi>ſeaſon,</hi> applicable to the <hi>preſent,</hi> and leave the <hi>notional</hi> to our book-men; whoſe volumes calculated for all cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates ſwell big againſt the Evils of the Rule of <hi>Many</hi> or <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocracy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mine ſhall be appropriate to this Iſland, which indeed is a large Continent, abundantly populous, and govern'd by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a ſort of people that live <hi>plentifully</hi> and at <hi>eaſe</hi> upon their rents, extracted from the toyl of their Tenants and ſervants; In Law-phraſe they are inſtil'd the <hi>minor Nobility,</hi> in Engliſh <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> each of whom within the bounds of his own eſtate acts the <hi>Prince;</hi> he is purely abſolute; his ſervants and labourers are in the nature of his <hi>Vaſſals;</hi> his Tenants indeed are free, but in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152860:4"/>nature of <hi>Subjects,</hi> whom he orders in his Courts, draws ſupplies from by his Fines, and awes by his power and <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>fealty</hi> to infinite ſubmiſſion. The more his Mannors are, and the more indulgent he behaves himſelf, like a good Prince, the larger is his Territory, and the more awful his commands. A Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour more rich and potent, gives check to his inferiour Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and brings his petty Prince-ſhip into awe; and perhaps he again is awed by a greater and more powerful in eſtate or friends. But none of theſe with reſpect to his quality and eſtate will admit a parity with his inferiour Neighbours, much leſs his Tenant or Dependant.</p>
               <p>Into this Ranck do our Commanders, Citizens, and Burghers aſpire to be inroll'd; ſo that no ſooner by Arms, Office, or Trade, do they acquire a competent ſtock, but forthwith for Land it is diſpoſed; and then diſowning the Title of Souldiers, Citizens, or Burghers, they take to themſelves the degree and name of Gentlemen, with Armes not improper; for <hi>England within</hi> it ſelf has been ſo often ſhuffled from <hi>high to low,</hi> that ſcarce any Artificer but may find his name in the <hi>Heralds</hi> book, though not his Pedegree, which <hi>ingenuity</hi> and <hi>goodwill</hi> may eaſily ſupply: And thus being aequipt with a <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Eſtate,</hi> they ſet up ſutably the dominion within their Territories, which none can diſpute, becauſe they have no right to intermeddle with what whoſoever has or does within himſelf: For by Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, I intend not only ſuch as are ſo in <hi>blood,</hi> but ſo in <hi>quality;</hi> ſuch as live eaſefully, and like Princes upon the labours of the dependants.</p>
               <p>Now that this ſort of people have by influence and in effect the <hi>Command</hi> of this Nation, at this inſtant appears evident, in this, That they ſit at the Helm in the <hi>Supreme Council;</hi> they command <hi>in chief</hi> at Sea and Land; they impoſe <hi>Taxes,</hi> and levy it by Commiſſioners of the ſame quality: Out of this ranck felect we Sheriffs, Juſtices of Peace, and all that execute the authority of a <hi>Judge;</hi> By the influence of which powers, they ſo order all elections to Parliament or otherwiſe, that the whole Counties follow their reſpective factions, and the Commonalty in the Votes are manag'd by them, as the horſe by his <hi>Rider.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that as the <hi>Agrarian</hi> or intereſt of land is principally in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152860:5"/>this rank, ſo is the conſequence thereof, <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand,</hi> which imboldens them to ſuch a height of ſpirit, <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to our Gentry,</hi> as they are too apt to undervalue perſons of inferiour quality, Burgeſſes, and Mechanicks, with whom to inter-marry by our old Law, it was a <hi>disparagement</hi> for a <hi>Ward;</hi> and this ſpirit of generoſity cannot be ſuppreſt, 'tis ſo rivited in their <hi>nature,</hi> but by the eradication of their <hi>perſons,</hi> or at leaſt, their <hi>qualities;</hi> to which barbarous effect, I have known ſome <hi>Grandees</hi> have pleaſed to vent a ſence.</p>
               <p>For indeed the eſtabliſhing of a <hi>Free-ſtate</hi> is otherwiſe deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; and therefore it was the courſe that the prevailing Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanicks amongſt the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> were inforc't to take: How elſe ſhall we be levell'd to a <hi>parity,</hi> which is of the very eſſence of a Free-ſtate? For as Titles and Honour are incident to a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> ſo equality in place, degree, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rth, are to <hi>Democra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> unleſs where in caſe of <hi>Office,</hi> for the time only they are intitled to precedency. Reduc'd muſt the Gentry be to the Condition of the Vulgar; <hi>Commons</hi> already are they in <hi>Title,</hi> which is but a fallacy of the name, and deludes our Statiſts; for indeed they are ſo only <hi>Repreſentatively,</hi> being rather the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunes</hi> and leaders of the peoples ſtrength, and the governors of their purſe, than <hi>purely Commons.</hi> Nor will it ſuffice to obtain this <hi>parity,</hi> unleſs with it alſo we eſtabliſh our <hi>Supreme Power</hi> in a body corporate, compacted, and permanent; ſuch as is that of <hi>London,</hi> where poſſibly the Grandeur of that City, had it ſpirit and deſign, might erect it ſelf into a Free-ſtate, and might by that great Magazin of treaſure and men there <hi>imbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died,</hi> give Law to the whole people ſcattered as they are in a large continent. Having firſt reduced ſome meet Cities, Forts, and Caſtles, which being Gariſoned from the <hi>Head Colony,</hi> will awe the Countryes, and order them into a vaſſalage competent to make up a Free-ſtate: But we of the <hi>Gentry,</hi> ſhall neither have the honour of the <hi>name,</hi> nor benefit of the <hi>thing.</hi> 'Twill be inſtiled the Common-wealth of <hi>London,</hi> not of <hi>England;</hi> and our pay muſt be as they impoſe, and our liberty as they vouchſafe it; only <hi>in this</hi> it will be the leſs agreeable, that we are ſubject to our <hi>Inferiours.</hi> This Diſcourſe, though it ſeems Drollery, yet has not bin without its jealouſie among the wiſe, when in time that great City ſhall be compelled by our confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152860:5"/>to know its own ſtrength, and by that its intereſt, when neceſſity to preſerve it ſelf, will imbolden them to lay hands on others, and ſo inforce <hi>Ord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r</hi> upon them that can give <hi>none</hi> unto themſelves.</p>
               <p>From this <hi>Embrio</hi> have iſſued thoſe Common-wealths which are ſo fam'd in notions; as thoſe of <hi>Rome, Carthage, Athens, Lacedemon, Corinth, Thebes, &amp;c.</hi> Great Cities of that name, which have ſubdued their adjacent Territories, and denominated the dominion, wherein only thoſe of the freedome, <hi>Citizens</hi> and <hi>Denizens</hi> had <hi>vote</hi> or <hi>power;</hi> The Gentlemen, as we of the Countyes, being purely tributary to the Grand City; unleſs we tranſplant our ſelves, renounce our Titles, and ſo by degrees advance into the honour of a <hi>Burgeſs,</hi> as we now do exerciſe our <hi>junior</hi> iſſue. And ſuch are at this day the fam'd Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice, the United Provinces,</hi> the <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> not to inſtance in thoſe petty States of <hi>Genoa, Rugaſa, Geneva, &amp;c.</hi> All Common-wealths, moſt denominated from thoſe principal Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes which give the Law to the adjacent Provinces. Thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Swiſſes,</hi> though they derive not ſo directly their Title from one City, yet are they in ſubſtance of the ſame compoſure, being only an united Body of <hi>corporated</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, combin'd in one for mutual defence againſt invaders; but of an equal power to impoſe upon the adjacent Territories, ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuate under the awe of each reſpective City, or Town-Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</p>
               <p>It falls not within my memory that there ever was, or at this day is a <hi>Free-State</hi> in the world, that's managed by the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> inhabiting at large, or by any people not combin'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Juriſdiction of their <hi>Walls,</hi> except the <hi>Griſons,</hi> who are a ſcattered people, of a mean quality, having long ſince diſown'd their Gentry, without walled Town or Gariſon; 'Tis a ſmall Territory, poſſibly of extent to an inland County; Upon Emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, the whole people at a ſet day meet in the open ayre, where the <hi>major vote,</hi> as we Knights of the ſhire, cryes up the Magiſtrates, and determines War. Their confuſion makes them eaſie for conqueſt, were their Country worth it, and not ſecured by the <hi>united Cantons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now to apply the premiſes; Can we ſuppoſe the Gentry that are now in power, will admit a <hi>parity,</hi> will <hi>level</hi> their degree
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152860:6"/>and dominion to a proportion with their <hi>Copy-holder?</hi> Nay, will renounce the <hi>wearing</hi> of a <hi>Sword,</hi> and learn to <hi>make one?</hi> will ſubmit to become tributary to the Neighbour Colony? Then poſſibly may we aſpire from the ſtate of <hi>Kingſhip</hi> to a free-ſtate in <hi>Clownſhip;</hi> or at beſt from the free-giving of <hi>ſudſidies</hi> to the <hi>Majeſty</hi> of a <hi>Scepter,</hi> to the forc'd-payment of <hi>exciſe</hi> to the <hi>High-mighty Burgher;</hi> Such as was that High and mighty <hi>But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> who of late was Commiſſionated by the <hi>Swiſses</hi> as one of the Chiefs to be <hi>Godfather</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> Kings ſon.</p>
               <p>But 'twill be ſaid, as <hi>Plato</hi> fancyed his Community, and <hi>Sir Thomas Moor his Utopia,</hi> ſo may we a <hi>Rotation,</hi> thereby to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther up a new Model of a Common-wealth out of the ſcattered <hi>Gentry</hi> in the nature of a <hi>Houſe of Commons.</hi> Truly my friends, if you will try new experiments, I wiſh you had other ſubjects to practice upon, than the <hi>Estates,</hi> and <hi>Lives,</hi> nay, the very <hi>Souls</hi> of Chriſtians: We have run the <hi>loſs</hi> of thoſe, and the <hi>hazard</hi> of theſe too long upon the hopes of a <hi>Chimera</hi> in the braines of ſome. The word <hi>Liberty</hi> has deluded us into patience, and patience ſince 48. has brought forth not leſs payments, but more ſervitude.</p>
               <p>We are obſtructed, you'l ſay, ſo that we are not permitted to foſter up our <hi>Babe</hi> to full perfection: And <hi>ſtill</hi> are you like to be; for the wiſe foreſee the <hi>Evil</hi> of ſuch a State, and contrive with as much deſign to prevent it, as the unadviſed to bring it on: Yet from 48. to 53. you had it from the <hi>Nurſe,</hi> and might in five years have ſet it upon its <hi>Feet,</hi> but that you found the <hi>ſweet</hi> of ingroſſing <hi>Power</hi> to your ſelves: No indeed, could it ſtand <hi>without you,</hi> which might be evident from the high <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> and the great <hi>ſcorne</hi> you were reproach't with, when it was diſſolv'd; Not one <hi>bloody noſe</hi> in the defence of that <hi>High and Mighty State;</hi> Nor ſcarce a good thought ſince of any of the perſons: For your late <hi>twice</hi> advancement, I ſuppoſe, e're this you are ſenſible, that it was only to ſerve a <hi>turn,</hi> as a thing fit to be made a <hi>property:</hi> Do'nt you believe that it was deſire of your Rule, but of a <hi>farther</hi> change, that inſpirited the people againſt the <hi>Army,</hi> when you poſſibly as <hi>next at hand,</hi> moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the empty Saddle, but you were not warm in the <hi>ſeat,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with a publick leave you were <hi>unhorſt,</hi> witneſs the <hi>Bonfires</hi> that might have lighted you to the <hi>Lands end,</hi> if you had dared to come among them.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152860:6"/>
               <p>Now, though I diſown thoſe <hi>irregular</hi> tranſactions, yet they ſtrongly <hi>tye</hi> me in this ſence, that as this Government was ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally founded in a <hi>ſingle</hi> perſon, ſo the <hi>Genius</hi> of the people ſtill adheres to the ſame foundation. Examine we the various revolutions that have hapned, <hi>Britans, Romans, Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans;</hi> or more neerly the changes in their deſcendents from the <hi>direct</hi> line to the <hi>Collateral;</hi> or neerer, the times of inſurrection, <hi>depoſing</hi> Kings, <hi>Edward</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> both the ſeconds of the Name, and we ſhall find <hi>Kingſhip</hi> ſtill in faſhion: Nay, that of King <hi>John</hi> is more notorious; for when the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple had in a ſort dethroned that King, and ſworne allegeance to <hi>Lewis</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> yet when <hi>John</hi> dyed, the people not only expell'd the forraigner, but having power in their own hands, they Crowned his <hi>Sonne</hi> an infant, without power or adherents: And not one ſyllable in <hi>all our</hi> Chronicles, of a deſign or endeavour to erect a Free-ſtate; No not when <hi>Wat Tiler,</hi> or <hi>Jack Straw</hi> revell'd it with their Clownes. Is our <hi>Genius</hi> changed? you will find it, <hi>No.</hi> Did you not obſerve it in the laſt <hi>Protector,</hi> who in a ſingle perſon bearing up but the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of Kingſhip, was ſo ſeconded by a full Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, that had he not bin betrayed by his own puſillanimity, and the power of a corrupted Army, he had bin ſufficiently ſecured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>State Zelots.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis not the ſence or intereſt of a <hi>few,</hi> that can long ſway a Nation. If the <hi>publick spirit</hi> be averſe, at the long runne it will prevaile. The more diſpute there is with that ſpirit, the more imbitter'd it will be found; for whatever we dream, even when the <hi>multitude</hi> have the power, the command is in a <hi>Few.</hi> The active ſpirits lead the <hi>herd,</hi> and ingroſs the place, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and the ſway: This in a generous mind begers <hi>diſdain,</hi> and that <hi>faction;</hi> for when all are equal, thouſands think themſelves as deſerving Rule, as thoſe that carry it. To ſatisfie <hi>all,</hi> it is impoſſible; to pleaſe <hi>few,</hi> diſpleaſes the moſt. Our tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſince 48, have made this as ſenſible, as we have made our ſelves <hi>despicable.</hi> To conclude, The <hi>Engliſh Gentry</hi> have Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits <hi>pure,</hi> naturally <hi>juſt,</hi> and <hi>Generous;</hi> like fire aſpiring as a <hi>Pyramide,</hi> from low to high, and it will never reſt, till it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts it ſelf unto a <hi>Unity</hi> at top: So God is <hi>One,</hi> or he were not God, nor could he rule the world. He that likes not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152860:7"/>that <hi>preſident,</hi> but delights in the Rule of <hi>many,</hi> let him begin a Preſident <hi>in his family,</hi> and he may there poſſibly have <hi>enough</hi> to do.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>Miſchiefs incident to our endeavours for a</hi> Free-State.</head>
               <p>THough we cannot fix a ſettlement of a State, yet poſſibly by Artifice and Contrivance ſome may continue a <hi>Rotation</hi> in diſorder: As Boys at <hi>Foot-ball,</hi> now one, then another trip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping up the heels, and carrying away the Ball: Some perhaps that out-run their fellows, may hit the <hi>mark,</hi> and ſuck the <hi>ſweet,</hi> till being full-gorg'd, they grow <hi>Lazy;</hi> and ſome em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty ones that are more active, mount their Roomes. In the mean time, we their tributaries are attacht with theſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs.</p>
               <p n="1">1. We ſhall conſtantly live under the affrights of an <hi>invaſion</hi> from abroad; for while any of that Royal Line ſurvive, we may well judge that they contrive a <hi>Restauration:</hi> And our Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men have bin <hi>ſo kind</hi> to Him, as not to give his Home-party a <hi>full oblivion;</hi> but againſt true policy and preſident, do conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue them <hi>diſabled,</hi> and ſo in diſcontent. Hence is it, that we muſt be alwayes jealous not aſſured of our <hi>next</hi> Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, till an equal ſufferance begets an equal ſence.</p>
               <p n="2">2. While we groan under this fear, 'tis of neceſſity that we continue a conſiderable <hi>Force</hi> at <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Sea;</hi> which lying idle, will corrupt as ſtanding water in a Pool, and endanger a <hi>new</hi> combuſtion, as they are blown up by their preſent <hi>Maſter:</hi> However like our old <hi>Lord-Danes,</hi> they will be burthenſome to the Country by their Quartering, and conſequently odious: Or otherwiſe to keep the Souldiery in action, we muſt either affright them, upon the diſcovery of a <hi>new-fain'd-plot,</hi> or engage them in a <hi>forraign</hi> War; To this are the united Provinces in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forc't, to prevent Kingſhip in the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> though their ſcituation ſecures their <hi>Burgher ſhips</hi> much ſtronglier than
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152860:7"/>can ours; for their Dominion conſiſts chiefly in <hi>ſtrong</hi> Cariſons, Fortified Townes, and thoſe in a ſmall circuit; ſhould one or more of them be ſurprized by a <hi>buſie</hi> Army, the reſt will take the <hi>Alarm,</hi> and prevent their progreſs by the force of Walls and Bulwarks, not to be maſtered but by <hi>Seiges</hi> tedious, and more <hi>expenſive,</hi> than ten ſuch Princes can advance: But in <hi>England</hi> an open continent, he that Commands the field, Rules the purſe; for <hi>London</hi> is too rich to have courage, and will more readily ſubmit to the <hi>will</hi> of the Commander, than to the <hi>modeſty</hi> of his Army.</p>
               <p n="3">3. While we have ſuch fears, and ſuch an Army, we muſt continue <hi>contribution,</hi> beſides thoſe great <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Exciſe,</hi> which impoveriſh us, though not ſo ſenſibly, yet more bitterly than the <hi>Tax;</hi> for the commodity being charged, the price is raiſed, and the buyer even almoſt in every thing that he eats, drinks, or wears, payes the <hi>account.</hi> I remember when Mr. <hi>Pym</hi> that grand Patriot, upon neceſſity but mentioning the word <hi>Exciſe</hi> in the Houſe of Commons, was by a young ſpirit, and not without applauſe, called to the <hi>Barre.</hi> What then we eſteemed <hi>Poyſon,</hi> we take now as <hi>Phyſick;</hi> but in that Age it ſeem'd impoſſible that a <hi>free-born</hi> Engliſh-man could have ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed it. 'Twas begot in the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> with their State which makes them <hi>Free;</hi> that is, in <hi>Purſe,</hi> not in <hi>Priviledge:</hi> for no <hi>Engliſh King</hi> dar'd ever demand, what they are inforc't to pay. Now conſider we what benevolences, Sequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, five and twentieth parts, a Tax of fifty ſubſidies at once, Fines and Compoſitions, Sales of Kings, Biſhops, Deans and Chapters, and Delinquents Lands, the two parts of Papiſts, nay a ſhare of our <hi>very charities</hi> to the diſtreſſed, beſides con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant contributions that have been levied: How has it all been devoured by the <hi>Armies,</hi> whoſe belly indeed has no bottome! yet what <hi>Arrears</hi> to them do we owe? what a Debt have we contracted? 'tis judged not leſs than <hi>Three Millions!</hi> Leſſen the Army we dare not; then muſt we <hi>ſupply</hi> it in proportion, or permit <hi>free-quarter</hi> which is worſe; for the Souldier muſt <hi>live,</hi> and he cannot by the <hi>aire.</hi> Whence ſhall we acquire this vaſt Sum? not leſs certainly can our conſtant charge be, than <hi>two millions</hi> by the year, beſides the intereſt of the great debt which ſwells dayly; we have the <hi>ill luck</hi> that none will <hi>Rebel,</hi> that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152860:8"/>we may have Lands to <hi>Sequeſter,</hi> none to fell; Cuſtoms ſink, and ſo will the Exciſe. All for the future (if the Army conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue) muſt be extorted by contribution from the ſtarveling Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries. But I doubt, as there is little <hi>Will</hi> to it, ſo there is leſs <hi>ability;</hi> Their patience has bin exerciſed to the height; Take heed; <hi>Neſcit plebs jejunatimere,</hi> as ambition has no <hi>bounds,</hi> ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity has no <hi>Barre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Pay;</hi> How is it poſſible they ſhould, if <hi>Trade</hi> fails; Our ſubſiſtence in the Country, hangs ſenſibly on commerce in the City. Obſerve it in one commodity; How can the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man expect his Rent, when his Tenant cannot ſell his <hi>Wool?</hi> If wool be not ſold, how can the <hi>poor</hi> (millions of poor) be ſet on work? If the poor be not ſet on work, they muſt <hi>ſteal,</hi> or <hi>ſtarve;</hi> If the <hi>Cloathyer</hi> can vent no Cloth, how can he buy the Wool? If the <hi>Merchant</hi> have not a free and well-orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Trade,</hi> how can he buy cloth? The miſcarriages of theſe times has ſpoyled the Trade of our Cloth beyond the ſeas; ſo that unleſs we return into order, and awe our Neighbours to a ſutable correſpondence, 'tis not recoverable. For other trades how they ſink, may be evident from the dayly <hi>ruptures</hi> that are ſpoken of; and more fully from the 2000. ſail that we have loſt fince the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> War. Now, the commodities we have thence we take in upon <hi>retaile</hi> from our Officious <hi>Neighbour,</hi> who knows handſomly to foment the difference, and reap the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. Our gold walks beyond Sea more freely than in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Forraign Trade we pay for <hi>dear;</hi> Home-commodities we ſell <hi>cheap.</hi> 'Tis not poſſible but the wealth of <hi>England</hi> ſinks in value conſiderably every year: No Trade can be, till there be a ſettlement; No ſettlement, while we dance every day to a new <hi>Whiſtle.</hi> There are ten models in propoſal, and every <hi>faction</hi> is with blood ready to avow his <hi>way</hi> the beſt. While we thus ſtagger, we may ſhortly expect to be accoſted with the ſame <hi>dilemna,</hi> that a poor labourer put upon my Tenant the other day, from whoſe <hi>fold,</hi> week after week he had ſtoln a <hi>ſheep;</hi> he freely confeſt the Theft, and told him, work he had <hi>none,</hi> nor could get <hi>any,</hi> though he offered to labour at leſs value than he was <hi>wont;</hi> worth he was no more than his <hi>earthen pot;</hi> ſteal he muſt; hang him he might, but he his wife and five children would not <hi>ſtarve,</hi> while they had hands to <hi>take.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152860:8"/>
               <p n="5">5. Were it poſſible to keep down the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of the Engliſh, which has been ſo imbitter'd by the violent inſtruments of our <hi>Statiſts,</hi> what ſhall we think of <hi>Ireland,</hi> who already Act in a ſence altogether averſe to our new model? Nay, what of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a free people, no way in Vaſſalage to us, unleſs upon the account of our <hi>late Conqueſt:</hi> Can we think thoſe two Kingdomes will <hi>truckle</hi> under this? Certainly, they wait but opportunity, and when it comes, 'twil coſt us <hi>dear:</hi> Their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt undoubtedly is <hi>Kingſhip,</hi> whereby they may poſſibly hope to have an influence upon the <hi>ſweets</hi> of our Court. While thus we are imbroyl'd with fears and Wars to ſubdue our tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries, our purſes and blood muſt be at the <hi>expenſe,</hi> and our enemies abroad will work their intereſts.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Was not the maintenance of our <hi>fundamental</hi> Laws, the pretence of our <hi>quarrel?</hi> Found we not the ſpirit of the Nation rowz'd up upon the found of the <hi>Trumpet? Popery,</hi> was it not decry'd? and Religion, <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion adjudg'd to be in danger? were we not call'd up to the Battel upon the account of Zeale with a <hi>Curſe ye Meroz?</hi> Now if we truck on in the ſearch for a <hi>Free-ſtate;</hi> as for Religion, ſo much of it as we may call <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> muſt of neceſſity turn to <hi>Wantonneſs;</hi> for our diviſions are ſo great already, that we dare not exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate by advancing <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> Nay, indeed <hi>we cannot</hi> if we dar'd; for the moſt <hi>active</hi> of our Statiſts (if they have any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion) 'tis that of the Sectary, which they own as the maine ſupporter of their <hi>Model,</hi> whoſe intereſt it is, to give <hi>Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> to all. As for <hi>Laws,</hi> thoſe which we adored for the excellency and antiquity, muſt of neceſſity be alter'd in our Freedomes of <hi>perſon</hi> and <hi>eſtate,</hi> wherein true liberty is princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally concern'd: Thus, if we have a free-ſtate in the way of a Houſe of Commons <hi>alwayes,</hi> or a Council in the interval; that Soveraign Court will take power to impoſe <hi>Taxes,</hi> and to impriſon <hi>perſons:</hi> Now by the Law of <hi>England</hi> no free-man could be <hi>taxed</hi> or <hi>impreſt,</hi> but by <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and regularly paſt by the <hi>three</hi> eſtates, and he intruſted the elected to conſent only ſo far as by <hi>Common Council</hi> of the <hi>three eſtates</hi> ſhould be agreed: In paſſing whereof, the Commons were as the Tribunes of the people, as their <hi>Bulwark</hi> againſt high payments and impreſſures demanded by the Prince; To
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152860:9"/>whoſe occaſions they would not contribute, unleſs well ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the neceſſity and disburſement; which granted, they had the ſame concernment therein with the <hi>whole</hi> people, that is, To <hi>pay,</hi> and to be <hi>impreſt.</hi> Now when the Commons are grown <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign,</hi> who ſhall we call upon to be our <hi>Tribunes?</hi> for the ſame perſons that have the <hi>power</hi> to raiſe, have in effect the <hi>priviledge</hi> to disburſe. And how little will they value thoſe <hi>ſmall</hi> ſhares which they pay in their Rents, when they ſhall aſſuredly receive <hi>large</hi> ſalaries by their imployments? For believe it, though eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Stateſman has not <hi>preferment,</hi> yet the moſt conſiderable will be in <hi>pay,</hi> and thoſe are leaders to the reſt. Upon this account it is, that while a Parliament ſits, we ſhall be in <hi>conſtant pay;</hi> for the leaders will ſtrain for a deſign, rather than want a preferment; And we the people may perhaps complain of the Reiterated bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then; but to whom ſhall we <hi>appeal?</hi> As for our perſons, by our known Lawes, we could not be impriſon'd, but by a <hi>regular</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in a courſe of juſtice, or a <hi>full Act</hi> of Parliament. An <hi>ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> there ought to be, and thereupon a <hi>Bayl,</hi> unleſs the cauſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd not baylable by the Warrant; when the accuſed had free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to make <hi>defence</hi> upon peruſal of his charge; if injuſtice or malice appear'd in that proſecution, his reparation was ready and uſual. Otherwiſe than thus, could not a Houſe of Commons ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally proceed, unleſs poſſibly upon their <hi>own members,</hi> which is diſputable; but an impeachment muſt be drawn, and a trial had before <hi>the Lords</hi> as a Court of Juſtice. Should the King, or the Council <hi>commit</hi> an Engliſh man, it was upbraided as an Act of Tyranny. What becomes of this eminent freedom under a <hi>free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> when upon ſlight ſuggeſtions of a <hi>spightful</hi> Neighbor that is in power, the <hi>Serjeant</hi> at Armes ſeizes us with his exorbitant <hi>fees!</hi> No bayl, no <hi>Habeas Corpus,</hi> no regular way of juſtice to do us right. And there poſſibly, after a twelvemonth, if we have good friends, and can humble our ſelves to our potent Adverſary, may we get diſcharg'd, but without <hi>amends</hi> or knowing of our <hi>Crime:</hi> And this courſe muſt be continued upon <hi>Reaſon of State.</hi> Lo thus while we cajol our ſelves with the name of Freedom, we loſe the thing, and become <hi>free</hi> only to be made <hi>ſlaves.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152860:9"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The happineſſe of a compoſure with the right Heir of the</hi> Crown.</head>
               <p>INſtance I might more, but theſe being plainly and ſenſibly miſchievous, may ſuffice. Enquire we now into the way of cure; And things certainly are reduc'd to that ill temper, that tis far more eaſie to demonſtrate what <hi>may be evil,</hi> than what <hi>will be good;</hi> but comparing times with things, I doubt not to evidence but that a cloſure with the way of Kingſhip is much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be embrac'd as that which <hi>may be good,</hi> than that confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which certainly <hi>will be evil;</hi> And dream we not of cloſing the difference by erecting a ſingle perſon of a <hi>new line;</hi> for that will <hi>leſsen</hi> the party, in that it makes the quarrel <hi>perſonal,</hi> and will the more diſguſt the ſpirits of this generous people, in that they are ſubjected to their <hi>Equal,</hi> who to retain his uſurpation, will be enforc'd to accumulate thoſe violences whereof we had ſad experience under the <hi>old Protector;</hi> otherwiſe he ſhall ſoon be made the object of our <hi>contempt,</hi> as was his ſon with his eaſie and gentle way of acting; Nor will the afore-recited miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs be at all prevented; for our <hi>fears</hi> will be the ſame, and conſequently our <hi>charge.</hi> It reſts only that we cloſe with the right Heir of the Crown upon termes conducible to aſſurance; And yet not ſuch as may ſo much abridge the juſt rights of the Crown as to <hi>advance</hi> a licentiouſneſs in the people; for with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber men, who weigh the reaſon of things, a <hi>Negative</hi> in the Prince, is a moſt <hi>ſecure</hi> preſervative of Peace to the people; and the people have as much <hi>comfort</hi> under the Protection of his juſt Prerogative, as they have <hi>benefit</hi> by their own priviledges; Nor will <hi>unreaſonable</hi> terms that are impoſed be farther continued than they are inforc'd; only therefore ſecuring againſt <hi>revenge,</hi> let the old Laws be the <hi>ſtandard</hi> between both, and thoſe duly executed, will ſufficiently, and without entrenchment ſecure both; From ſuch a cloſure probably will reſult theſe advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152860:10"/>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Peace</hi> enſues, and thence <hi>Plenty;</hi> No jealouſie of a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender to invade us from abroad; <hi>Ireland,</hi> yea and <hi>Scotland</hi> will acquieſce by way of ſubordination to the Crown; the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al party muſt ſubmit to the termes agreed; For if the <hi>Head</hi> be ſatisfied, the <hi>body</hi> hath neither power nor title to diſpute it far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Parties reconcil'd, what neceſſity is there of a Land-Army? the <hi>Militias</hi> without charge in every County being ſecur'd in hands of <hi>confidence,</hi> ſo that ſuch of the ſouldiery who make <hi>war</hi> their <hi>trad,</hi> may have leaſure to be imployed <hi>at Sea,</hi> where need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful it will be that we continue a conſiderable Fleet, as the <hi>Walls of England;</hi> and to preſerve that Soveraignty at Sea which is our ancient right; the reſt being paid their <hi>arrears,</hi> may chearfully retire to their wives and friends.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This horrid <hi>Tax,</hi> yea and the <hi>Exciſe</hi> may ſhortly ceaſe; for I ſhall anon evidence that a Revenew may be advanc'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either of theſe, fully competent to ſupport the <hi>Court-expence,</hi> and the neceſſities of the Publick; only at preſent it will be needful that we impoſe one great <hi>Tax,</hi> ſuppoſe we a twelve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>months contribution to be paid at once, therewith to pay the <hi>arrears</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> and disband them <hi>honourably;</hi> Theſe ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears muſt at laſt be paid, if we intend juſtice to thoſe that are in <hi>power</hi> to command it; nor can there be any way but this cloſure <hi>to get them paid;</hi> otherwiſe, as their pay grows, ſo will their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears, and increaſe dayly; better were it that at once we take a ſtrong purge, than live contributing till we conſume beyond the cure of phyſick.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A Peace with <hi>forraign Princes</hi> is a certain conſequent of this cloſure, having a Prince ſo related in <hi>blood,</hi> nay of the <hi>high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt extraction</hi> in the Chriſtian world, and he grown formidable in the conjunction of all intereſts; for he rules a people that have been <hi>diſciplin'd</hi> in war, which on both ſides have given ſuch evidence of a <hi>courage,</hi> that will be the terror of the world, were we drawn off from worrying our own bowels; were we all uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in <hi>love,</hi> as in <hi>ſubjection;</hi> which poſſibly by time and a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet <hi>receding</hi> on each ſide may be accompliſh'd; as then we ſhall be awful, ſo ſhall we be courted to alliances, which may be accepted, as may conduce to the intereſt of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> From hence flows <hi>Trade,</hi> and thence wealth to an Iſland; that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152860:10"/>which we hold now by <hi>retaile,</hi> and run with high hazards, may enrich us at the firſt hand, and without danger; nay, poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly we may turn the <hi>ballance,</hi> and our greedy neighbour may take his turn in the <hi>lighter</hi> ſcale.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We may attain to a condition wherein we may <hi>dare</hi> to own <hi>Religion,</hi> ſutable to thoſe of the <hi>Reformed</hi> party beyond the Seas; and thereby beget a confidence in them of our <hi>reality</hi> and <hi>adherence</hi> to the intereſt of the true Proteſtant Cauſe, when upon account of the Grandure of our State, and our opportune ſcituation we may become the <hi>head</hi> of that Party to enlarge the Territories of the Goſpel, and awe in a Toleration in our ways of worſhip, where they are moſt exploded; Let the Goſpel have free paſſage, and it will make <hi>its own way;</hi> for I diſown the promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it by the <hi>Sword,</hi> as totally unchriſtian, and bequeath it to the Turk.</p>
               <p n="6">6. This cloſure will in ſome ſort clear the <hi>integrity</hi> of ſuch as firſt engaged in the war; what was in pretence, but the defence of <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> which was afterwards model'd into words by a <hi>Solemn League</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> which if any, was the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> wherein the Covenanters ſwore to perſiſt, and not <hi>to ſuffer themſelves directy or indirectly, by whatſoever combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, perſwaſion or terror, to be divided or withdrawn, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make defection to the contrary party, or to give them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a deteſtable indifferency or neutrality in the Cauſe</hi> which was then judged ſo much to <hi>concern the glory of God, the good of the Kingdoms, and honour of the King, but that all the dayes of their lives zealouſly and conſtantly they would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue therein against all oppoſition, and promote the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their power againſt all lets and impediments what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever;</hi> which Covenant they then declared to make <hi>in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Almighty God, the ſearcher of all hearts, with a true intent to perform the ſame, as they ſhould anſwer it at the great day when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhould be diſcloſed;</hi> which Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant though poſſibly at firſt upon account of taking it <hi>without the Kings conſent,</hi> might not ſatisfie <hi>ſome,</hi> as to the manner of impoſing, yet ſince the <hi>matter</hi> of it may in ſubſtance be appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that the now <hi>King</hi> of Scots has <hi>there</hi> freely engaged therein, and may poſſibly conſent to an Act to that effect; will it not ſeem <hi>high perjury,</hi> and that we have juggled with the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152860:11"/>
                  <hi>world</hi> and our own <hi>ſouls,</hi> if we acquieſce not in the enjoyment thereof, which indeed comprehends all that <hi>reaſonable</hi> men can deſign; how ſhall we anſwer it to the great God, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence it was ſo ſolemnly entred with <hi>hands</hi> advanc'd? How ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous is it to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Cauſe? as if our Religion were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fit to be made a <hi>property</hi> to ſerve a <hi>turn;</hi> nay, how glorious will it be to thoſe <hi>brave ſupporters</hi> thereof, that maugre the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of head-ſtrong Statiſts, the Enthuſiaſmes of deluded Secta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, the violences of a tumultuous ſouldiery, they vindicate their <hi>firſt principles,</hi> and abandoning the ſuggeſtions of a private inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, to intend the <hi>Publick; That the world might bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> (for ſo they covenanted it ſhould) <hi>with their own conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of their loyalty, and that they had no thoughts or inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to diminiſh his Majeſties juſt power and greatneſs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>Reſolves to the grand Objections that ſeeme to obſtruct it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>GRand Objections I expect to be thrown in againſt this clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; I ſhall offer at ſome ſolutions, which poſſibly improv'd, may manifeſt that the difficulties are not ſo conſiderable, as thoſe that argue with a prejudice, pretend.</p>
               <div n="1" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> I. <hi>Purchaſers of Biſhops and Deans and Chapters lands are perſons many and of quality, and being in hazard to forgo their purchaſes, they will become diſcontented, and charge the State with falſhood, upon whoſe credit they disburſt their moneys.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> To diſcourſe ſoberly, and with reſpect to the ſtate of our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, I ſhall wave a diſpute, what Diſcipline in the Church, or whether any <hi>prefixt form</hi> by a <hi>Divine right?</hi> when the four grand pretenders, <hi>Papal, Epiſcopal, Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> ſhall reconcile the <hi>ſame</hi> texts, which <hi>all</hi> of them quote to a contrary tenent, poſſibly the world may be ſatisfied to cloſe with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152860:11"/>that which is approved. In the mean time it becomes diſcreet Rulers ſo to manage that intereſt, that there may be <hi>Order</hi> in the Church without <hi>Confuſion</hi> to the State.</p>
                  <p>Now as to us, if we inquire throughly, find we ſhall, that (whether it were the <hi>Innovations</hi> of the Prelacy, or their <hi>ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful expreſſions</hi> of the Gentry, or ſharp <hi>proſecutions</hi> of ſome more <hi>popular</hi> of the Miniſtry, or their intruſions upon the rights of the <hi>Common-Law,</hi> that gave the occaſion) The <hi>extirpation</hi> of that Hierarchy had a ſtrong influence in fomenting the <hi>firſt</hi> War, not therefore improperly inſtil'd <hi>Bellum Epiſcopale.</hi> If this were ſo, and that the power is gain'd by ſtrange providence, even to a miracle <hi>without blood,</hi> into thoſe hands that <hi>firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputed it,</hi> that have engag'd by <hi>Covenant</hi> to extirpate it, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but judge the reſtauration of the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> either in title or eſtate to be deſperate; much the rather ſince the King of <hi>Scots</hi> has ſo eminently bin drawn to declare his ſence that way, by engaging in that Covenant. And indeed ſince by an Act with the Kings <hi>Fiat,</hi> they are diſabled <hi>Votes</hi> in Parliament, the <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> nay, all coercive <hi>power</hi> (to abrogate which Law, will be of huge difficulty among the Commons) they have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle left them but the <hi>Name,</hi> to ſupport which, ſo vaſt a Revenew is not expedient. And their perſons, moſt of them being now <hi>dead,</hi> and none ſucceeding to the eſtate, a Purchaſer may enjoy his Bargaine with leſs reproach, than Delinquents Lands, where the <hi>Heire diſinherited,</hi> will lie always in the check.</p>
                  <p>Not that the Purchaſer ſhould only pamper himſelf by the <hi>miſeries</hi> of the times, and reap the <hi>full</hi> benefit of his fat <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi> but ſhould contribute a ſum conſiderable for the <hi>ſecuring</hi> of his Title. Thus, let him pay in to the publick uſe <hi>ſix years purchaſe</hi> of the full value, and then let his Title be confirm'd by a full Parliament. Intending this for <hi>Fee-ſimple,</hi> where there are leſs intereſts, there may be a proportionable <hi>pay.</hi> The reſult of this will be; A vaſt ſum raiſed to the <hi>Publick,</hi> without damage to the Purchaſer; for in ſubſtance he makes a new pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe: His Fee-eſtate with reſpect to the crazy Title, is not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable above 12. or 13. years purchaſe, and ſo it paſſes from man to man. Now when by this new disburſement he has his Title ſecur'd, his Fee-eſtate will be valuable 18. or 20. yeares
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152860:12"/>purchaſe, and ſo to be ſold from man to man; ſo that what he payes in <hi>mony,</hi> is repaid him in the <hi>value</hi> of his eſtate. This or the like expedient, conſidering how low they paid at firſt, what monyes they have rais'd ſince by Woods and perquiſits; what ſufferers we have bin in <hi>general</hi> throughout the Nation; may ſatisfie with reaſon the moſt <hi>greedy</hi> of thoſe Purchaſers. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable muſt be over-rul'd; for the private muſt be ballanc't by the publick.</p>
                  <p>With this, that the Purchaſers of <hi>Deans and Chapters</hi> Lands coming under the Act only of <hi>one Houſe,</hi> may be perſwaded to advance a higher proportion, to ſecure their Titles: And the monys by them paid, ought in <hi>juſtice</hi> to be disburſt for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Church in buying in <hi>Impropriations,</hi> being at firſt deſign'd for that end, to encourage <hi>learning.</hi> A <hi>lean</hi> mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance will in time produce a <hi>contemptible</hi> Miniſtry, even the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of the people, to the infamy of our Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> II. 'Tis farther argued, <hi>That if Kingſhip be reſtor'd, there muſt be a revenew ſutable to the ſplendour of the Court, and to ſupport his great alliance, when a Free-ſtate occaſions no ſuch expence; and the Kings revenew being now diſpoſed, he will become a vaſt burthen to the State.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Nothing more demonſtrative than that upon the <hi>foot</hi> of the account we ſhall find Kingſhip a great <hi>eaſe</hi> to the publick charge. We allotted the old Protector no leſs than a conſtant Revenew of 1900000. l. to ſupport the Government; yet that ſum at the <hi>yeares end</hi> clear'd not the account: Much more I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is now collected year by year out of the bowels of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and <hi>more we muſt,</hi> while we maintain an Army, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in feare, or engage in forraign War, which our <hi>active ſpirits</hi> will be too too apt to imbroyle us in from time to time, thereby ſome to feed <hi>ambition,</hi> others their <hi>purſes.</hi> And ſuch a ſpirit we reade of working in <hi>all Free-ſtates,</hi> Ancient, and Modern.</p>
                  <p>Compare we it with the expences of our old Courts; when <hi>the</hi> Kings Revenew in Lands, Perquiſits, and Cuſtoms, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not 700000. l. a year, it adorn'd it with a glorious Court, a
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152860:12"/>
                     <hi>noble aequipage</hi> for the honour of the Nation, and yet paid off a conſiderable <hi>Fleet,</hi> which has not bin much improv'd by our vaſt payments.</p>
                  <p>Senſible it is, that were the <hi>Crown-Lands</hi> reſtored, and the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> moderately ſetled, though not ſo inhanced as they now are to the ruine of <hi>Trade,</hi> thence might ariſe a ſufficient Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new to ſecure the <hi>Seas,</hi> and ſupply the <hi>Court:</hi> With this, that upon Emergencies if a <hi>Free Parliament</hi> ſaw cauſe, they might add a ſupply by the old way of <hi>Subſidie,</hi> or Contribution, if it ſeem more equal; which being but <hi>once</hi> paid, and in a <hi>mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> proportion and aſſent by a <hi>Free</hi> Parliament, and when Trade is <hi>free,</hi> and <hi>exciſe</hi> baniſht, would be rather a <hi>ſport,</hi> than a <hi>burthen,</hi> in compariſon of the monthly Tax.</p>
                  <p>Now for the <hi>Crown-Lands,</hi> I can inſtance ſeveral Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments wherein they have in <hi>re-aſſum'd,</hi> as not alienable, when a profuſe Prince has bin miſled by his Court-Paraſites, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his miſtake, has given them up to the <hi>fury</hi> of the people; for indeed thoſe Lands are in the Kings hands by way of <hi>trust,</hi> wherein his Subjects have a kind of <hi>intereſt;</hi> as well for ſafety, as for honour; which may intimate the <hi>weakneſs</hi> of their Title who purchaſed the ſame from the remainders only of the Houſe of Commons. Yet for the ſake of peace, why may they not come to a <hi>diſcount?</hi> and being re-imburſt their real purchaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money, with damages, diſcounting the mean profits, willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yield up that <hi>broken</hi> inheritance, wherein I and all true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhmen may pretend ſome intereſt. Something of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be offer'd for the recovery of thoſe we call <hi>Delinquents</hi> Lands. The late Treaty between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> gives a fair preſident, where the contrary parties whoſe eſtates were Sequeſtred and ſold, were <hi>re-inſtated</hi> in the juſt condition as the Lands then were at the promulgation of the peace, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny account for the mean profits.</p>
                  <p>Theſe Crown-Lands being thus re-aſſumed, will <hi>ſupply</hi> the Court and thoſe dependances; and for their re-purchaſe, why may not the monyes raiſed from the purchaſers of Biſhops Lands be imploy'd that way; or <hi>part</hi> of it, which will ſuffice? When the King wants more, let him be endear'd to his people for a ſupply; and that indeed was the <hi>good old way</hi> to redreſs our grievances, when we bought it by our purſes; and the bargain was no burthen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:152860:13"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> III. 'Tis argued, That <hi>Religion will be in hazard upon a cloſure with the King; His Mother is of the Romiſh party; He is now trained up amongſt them; nor can he do leſſe than gratifie the Popiſh with a toleration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> Nothing (doubtleſs) is of more concernment than the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of Religion;</hi> and for that part of it which is <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> this cloſure ſeems the only way to ſecure it: But we are not to hearken to ſuch as cry up <hi>Religion,</hi> and deſign <hi>Faction;</hi> that cry out <hi>Zeale</hi> for the Lord of Hoſts, when they intend <hi>ſelf-intereſt:</hi> To keep up a <hi>party,</hi> or an <hi>affected</hi> way, or to be the <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> of a Country; Religion has not at all proſper'd by undue pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices to advance it. 'Tis <hi>piety, meekneſſe, patience, humility,</hi> and thoſe graces of the Spirit that convince and convert, when rigidneſs, cenſuring, and the ſword exaſperate, and harden. But have we not a Parliament of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and the <hi>Militia</hi> in their hands to ſecure their Religion? Has not Gods <hi>power</hi> or truth <hi>evidence</hi> to ſecure it ſelf?</p>
                  <p>Certainly, the education of this <hi>Prince</hi> among that party, is not of <hi>choice;</hi> and ſhall our compulſion be term'd his <hi>crime?</hi> How averſe he has bin to the documents of his <hi>Mother,</hi> fame has ſufficiently made clear. Inquiſitions there have bin, and by him that was moſt concern'd, and kept intelligence abundant, as well into his <hi>Counſels,</hi> as his <hi>life;</hi> and never was he yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach't with <hi>debauchery</hi> in Religion or converſe. Nay, to a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, as if deſign'd by God for ſome great work, has he bin preſerv'd in <hi>perſon,</hi> and kept uncorrupt in <hi>Opinion,</hi> againſt the ſword on the <hi>one</hi> hand, and temptation on the <hi>other.</hi> A change of his Religion, would doubtleſs have engag'd him a powerful aſſiſtance from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> intereſt; which hitherto has ſeem'd rather to <hi>tyre out</hi> his conſtancy by ſufferance, than to <hi>reſent</hi> his miſery. The Jeſuite neither ſpeaks, nor acts indifferently as to his <hi>perſon;</hi> and you finde not many of the Romiſh way, that give him much applauſe, which argues a ſtrong fear in them of not much <hi>complacency</hi> in Him: It has bin their project, to <hi>crumble</hi> our Religion into <hi>Sects;</hi> upon hopes, that men finding no ſteddineſs in thoſe ſandy foundations which are built on the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152860:13"/>giddineſs of <hi>buſie</hi> ſpirits, and <hi>falſe lights,</hi> may at laſt fall off to their way of Popery, which ſeems more <hi>United</hi> upon account of their ſevere diſcipline.</p>
                  <p>And now that God after ſo many years contrivance, ſhould blowe off on a ſudden their whole deſignes, and reſtore things by ſtrange providence to their <hi>firſt principles,</hi> and ſome likelihood of good Order in the Church, and peace in the State, they ſeem confounded; and 'tis thought, will endeavour nothing more than the confuſion of the Prince, whoſe conjunction will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure it to poſterity. For well they know how he has bin le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctured by his <hi>Royal Father,</hi> as well as tutoured by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; which may enable him as to be the wiſeſt, ſo the moſt Religious Prince. You may read it thus,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I do require and entreat you as your Father, and your King, that you never ſuffer your heart to receive the leaſt check a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, or diſaffection from the true Religion eſtabliſh't in the Church of</hi> England; <hi>I tell you, I have tryed it; and after much ſearch and many diſputes, have concluded it to be the beſt in the world; not only in the community, Chriſtian; but alſo in the special notion as reformed; keeping the middle-way between the pomp of ſuperſtitious Tyranny, and the meanneſs of fantaſtick Anarchie: Not but that ſome lines as in very good figures may happily need ſome ſweetning and poliſhing, which might here have eaſily bin done by a ſafe and gentle hand,</hi> &amp;c. To this ſence ſpake he, when he had <hi>no more to speak.</hi> Now how in matters of conſequence this King has purſued elſewhere His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers documents, is ſenſible to him that <hi>reads</hi> and <hi>obſerves:</hi> And here in this is as manifeſt as the Sun, and he that diſputes it has more <hi>prejudice</hi> than <hi>reaſon;</hi> and ſuch ſingular Opinioniſts are not worth that ſatisfaction. As for his Mother, ſhe has had too much experience of the Engliſh ſpirits, and their averſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to her way, as to engage her Son upon that account to his ruine. If that way ſhe cannot <hi>now</hi> manage Him, how can ſhe, nay, how dare ſhe <hi>here?</hi> Nor indeed have her Relations in <hi>France,</hi> bin ſo propitious to <hi>Him,</hi> as to endear Him to <hi>Her:</hi> Witneſs His expulſion thence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="objection_and_answer">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152860:14"/>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                     </label> IV.
'Tis argued, That <hi>the Royal Family and that party have bin ſo highly diſoblig'd, that no Act of Oblivion can ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the oppoſites againſt revenge: What refuge is there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the anger of an inrag'd Prince, when he is once in power?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                     </label> I grant that there have bin provocations to the height: ſhall we therefore continue to <hi>provoke,</hi> becauſe we have <hi>begun?</hi> 'Tis a Rule indeed, That he that <hi>does wrong,</hi> never forgives, but he that <hi>has wrong, may.</hi> The intereſt of <hi>revenge</hi> is paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, but the intereſt of <hi>profit</hi> ariſes from a paſſion that prevails more. He's fooliſh that antepoſes <hi>rumour</hi> and <hi>empty</hi> paſſion, when it ſtands in competition with his <hi>ſafety;</hi> and this Prince under the tutourage of <hi>affliction,</hi> has bin educated in an Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of <hi>Wiſdome:</hi> He has eat hitherto as it were at the Almes of <hi>Charity,</hi> having not a <hi>Title</hi> of aſſurance to the Bed, he ſleeps on: A courſe of living abominated by a <hi>Royal Spirit,</hi> were not Neceſſity a Commander of all Laws: A Prince that has not <hi>perſonally</hi> bin diſguſted as his father; not knows he the face of <hi>many,</hi> that have bin inſtrumental to his hardſhips.</p>
                  <p>Now when a Prince from <hi>ſo low</hi> a depreſſure ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc't to the warmth of <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> he will be ſo ſenſible of that great and ſudden <hi>change,</hi> as to judge ſuch as have aſſiſted in his reſtauration, have fully obliterated the unkindneſs of their former oppoſitions; which perhaps too and not without rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, may be attributed to the prevalency or the falſhood of ſome Grandees now <hi>in the earth;</hi> or perhaps to, a miſtake of the true ſtate of things; for who is he that is not ſubject unto <hi>Errour?</hi> And if all miſtakes ſhould be corrected, I know not what man might paſs <hi>blameleſs.</hi> Much certainly of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs were contriv'd and driven up by a ſecret under-working of men, whom God in mercy has <hi>remov'd</hi> from being obſtacles to our peace.</p>
                  <p>To ſpeak home, Intereſt rules the <hi>whole</hi> world; and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as others, deſign more the <hi>ſecurity</hi> of their own greatneſs, than a petty <hi>revenge</hi> that may hazard it; eſpecially upon a Quarrel of their <hi>Anceſtorus,</hi> who being in Graves, can make no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152860:14"/>addreſs to move the paſſion. With us it is not, as in the caſe of <hi>Amaziah,</hi> who ſlew thoſe <hi>ſervants of his, that had ſlain his Father:</hi> There was only a conſpiracy of <hi>ſome few,</hi> amongſt us there is engag'd a grand Body of the <hi>three</hi> Nations. Should the Act of Oblivion (for that I preſume) be violated in the example of <hi>one perſon,</hi> upon that account <hi>all</hi> concern'd, would apprehend themſelves ready for the <hi>fetters;</hi> and what with <hi>fear,</hi> what with <hi>hate,</hi> ſuch a ſtorm would hazard to be rais'd, as might <hi>ſhake foundations.</hi> And Majeſty has felt ſo much the <hi>fury</hi> of the people, that it will hardly give occaſion to encounter it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
                  <p>But for this, ſearch we the experiences of the paſt Ages, and for preſidents we ſhall find two apt ones in the Hiſtories of the two Grand-fathers of the preſent King, <hi>Henry</hi> the great of <hi>France</hi> was oppoſed in his juſt Title by the <hi>Holy League;</hi> much the greater part of his Nobles were ingag'd to dethrone him: The City <hi>Paris, Roan,</hi> and the chief Citadels conſpir'd to his ruine; No leſs than <hi>ten</hi> ſet Battles were fought againſt his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; <hi>Paſquils</hi> and reproaches dayly gaul'd him: Obſerve the iſſue; After a long conteſt, they were <hi>both ſo wiſe,</hi> as to think a cloſure beſt: They conſent to Crown him, to deliver that high, puiſſant, and ſpirited Prince the power of the <hi>Militia:</hi> All ſubject themſelves by way of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and he ſoders all by a full Act of <hi>indempnity</hi> and <hi>Oblivion.</hi> Now being thus re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh't, and in full Soveraignty, he was ſo far from adventuring it upon a ſecond hazard by any violation, that he imploy'd <hi>thoſe very perſons</hi> that were his main oppoſites in his Armies, in his Offices, in his Councils: Nor do we reade of <hi>one of thoſe Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guers,</hi> that ever ſuffer'd affront or indignity by any reflection from that Prince: Nay, in his deep wiſdome he ſo indulg'd his Adverſaries, that his <hi>own party</hi> began to Quarrel him as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to them, whom notwithſtanding he honourably protected, yet not ſo eminently, as to <hi>raiſe jealouſies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly, there is no remark in our Hiſtories that ſo <hi>taints</hi> the memory of our great Queen, as the death of the <hi>Queen of Scots,</hi> who flying Mutiny, came hither as a diſtreſſed Princeſs, and was ingag'd <hi>Protection:</hi> But no ſooner was ſhe in our cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtody, than ſhe had reſtraints upon her, being denyed the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al preſence,</hi> which was ſo often promiſed her: Being thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152860:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Law of <hi>Nations,</hi> neither protected, nor ſet free to ſeek relief elſewhere, ſhe conceiv'd her ſelf authoriz'd by the Law of <hi>Nature</hi> to endeavour her <hi>eſcape;</hi> in contrivance whereof ſhe was diſcover'd, call'd to judgement being a lawful Princeſs, and no Subject, and by certain <hi>Lords</hi> prepared for that deſign, ſhe was in a private way condemned, and inforced to ſubject her Princely neck to the bloody <hi>Headſman.</hi> This her Son then King of <hi>Scots,</hi> ſeems highly to reſent, menaces <hi>revenge,</hi> ſends meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages, makes vows, and all to prevent that fatal ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ak, but to no effect. Obſerve the iſſue; Shortly Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> dyes, and thoſe very <hi>Lords</hi> that Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d perſonally in the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thers Death, Court the Son to the Crown, inveſt him in it, and he becomes eſtabliſhed with all prerogatives incident to the Engliſh <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>epter,</hi> What? Acts he in the way of revenge? No; He like a wiſe Prince feeling the warmth of ſo <hi>rich</hi> a climate, is ſo paſſionate to eſtabliſh his own greatneſs, that he not only forgets the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of His <hi>Mother,</hi> but manages his great affairs by the hands of thoſe <hi>very perſons</hi> that were contrivers of it: Yet through her <hi>blood</hi> did he derive his Title. Nor do we reade of one of thoſe Nobles or their progeny, that ſuffer'd <hi>diminution</hi> by any reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon that account. If then thoſe wiſe Princes that were verſt in the <hi>Art</hi> of Soveraignty, and inveſted with ſtrong pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thought fit notwithſtanding to lay aſide all animoſities for the preſerving their own <hi>Peace.</hi> What can we imagine of a <hi>young innocent Prince,</hi> who never yet felt the <hi>power</hi> of Soveraignty, who has bin trained up in <hi>ſucc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſive</hi> ſufferances, who comes in <hi>ſingly,</hi> and as it were at the <hi>devotion</hi> of His Opponents. Is it poſſible that he ſhould ſo much overſee his <hi>own intereſt,</hi> as to endeavour a violation of Oblivion; an Act that his moſt buſie enemies would <hi>ſtudy</hi> to engage him in, to colour up a <hi>new</hi> Quarrel; an Act that would yield him in the iſſue at beſt, the ſatisfaction of an empty and unprofitable paſſion, but by the miſcarriage might endanger Him from a Crown to <hi>nothing.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>His wiſe Father that had bin beaten into the knowledge of the Engliſh ſpirit, and foreſeeing this Objection, Lectures his. Son thus, <hi>Let no paſſion (my Son) betray you to any ſtudy of revenge upon thoſe, whoſe own ſin and folly will ſufficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them in due time; but as ſoon as the forked arrow of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152860:15"/>emulation is drawn out, uſe all Princely arts and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency to heal the wounds, that the ſmart of the cure may not equal the anguiſh of the hurt; Let Oblivion be granted not only as an act of State-policy, but of Chriſtian charity and choyce. It is all that I have left me, a power to forgive thoſe that have depriv'd me of all; and I thank God</hi> (writes the King) <hi>that I have a heart to do it, and joy as much in this grace which God has given me, as in all my former enjoyments, for to me it is a greater argument of Gods love, than my pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; Be confident</hi> (continues he) <hi>that the moſt of all ſides that have done amiſſe, have done ſo not out of malice, but miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rmation, or miſapprehenſion of things; None will be more loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to me or you, than thoſe ſubjects, who ſenſible of their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and our injuries will feel in their own ſouls moſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment motives to repentance, and earneſt deſires to make ſome reparations for their former defects:</hi> You may read more in the adviſe to his Son, which truly I cannot tranſcribe without a high compaſſion and reſentment; The like ſaid he at his <hi>laſt hour.</hi> But why doubt we? Is not the <hi>Militia</hi> in our hands, the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of Commands and Offices? Is not the <hi>Council</hi> at our recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation? Who dares reſiſt? nay, <hi>who can?</hi> If we ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a crime, and ſo fear revenge, I doubt, <hi>Compounders</hi> and <hi>free Contributers,</hi> that have ſtrengthned the arme of the adverſarie, are in ſtrict juſtice not altogether to be excuſed; Certainly we have been ſo ſhaken upon all intereſts by the <hi>late</hi> war, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but apparent ruine can engage us to it again; And better is it that all factions reſt ſatisfied with what they have ſuffered, as the <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ate</hi> of the times, than quarrelling upon old accounts to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyl our ſelves into a <hi>new</hi> ſufferance. He has a confidence much beyond mine, that either acting or looking on in theſe tranſactions can acquit himſelf of <hi>all guilt;</hi> ſuch a mask has been caſt over the <hi>face</hi> of things, ſuch temptations, ſuch force has aſſaulted men during theſe <hi>dark</hi> contextures of affairs, that it is paſt <hi>man</hi> to glide through all without a tincture of injuſtice; As it is beaſtly and unchriſtian paſſionately to perſevere in Error, ſo is it noble and Prince-like to forgive where there is the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of an Error: If we cannot truſt the nobleneſs of a Prince, nor the policy of government, nor the ſecurity of Laws, what fence can we raiſe againſt a <hi>fear;</hi> ſhall we conſume on, as incapable of a cure?</p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:152860:16"/>
                  <p>Truth is, while we live with men we ſhall be ſubject to that, which is the effect of their nature, <hi>Sin;</hi> nor is it poſſible to reap the more general fruit of the beſt eſtabliſhed policie, unleſſe by compact we ſubmit our ſelves to ſome poſſible <hi>inconveniences;</hi> As men we can erect nothing <hi>perfect;</hi> fix we muſt to that which ſeems moſt <hi>probable,</hi> and leave amendments to the experiences of time; yet this I dare aver, that this Government by <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Charta,</hi> and ſince, hath been ſo fortified with <hi>Laws</hi> as bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warks to prevent the inundation of Soveraignty: and that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution is <hi>ſo regular</hi> and adequate to that deſign, that as under the due execution thereof, the Engliſh man is born to the <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt freedom</hi> of the Chriſtian world, ſo no Prince ever attempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed any violation thereof, but at the long run, he ſuffer'd in that point of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> which let in the <hi>opportunity;</hi> Hence is it, that the rights of the people have from age to age grown <hi>ſtronger</hi> againſt the Prince, and ſometimes have hurried his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be a <hi>ſacrifice,</hi> alwayes his <hi>inſtruments;</hi> whereof few in our Hiſtories can we read, that contriving againſt the Law, have died in <hi>peaece;</hi> If poſſibly one Prince, as King <hi>Harry</hi> by his high ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ſweeps all before him, yet his Infant ſucceſſor was inforc'd to make amends for his violations; more eaſily may we diſpute our rights with a <hi>ſingle Prince,</hi> and his trembling Agents, than a knot of Soveraigns that are backt with the <hi>ſword.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Infinite hopes may we entertain that this Prince has been ſchool'd to underſtand his true intereſt; He has had glorious, though <hi>unhappy</hi> peſidents; He truly is moſt potent that is ſo <hi>in his ſubjects,</hi> not <hi>over</hi> his ſubjects; that is great <hi>in his people,</hi> not <hi>over</hi> his people; the one makes him contemned abroad, and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at home; the other makes him feared abroad, and beloved at home; Forraign enemies can rejoyce in nothing more than our <hi>ſelf-combuſtions,</hi> while we conſume that glorious ſpirit in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering our own bowels, which otherwiſe imploy'd, might be a <hi>terror</hi> to the world; Such exploits ſuit to the ancient glory of the Engliſh; this ſelf-murthering ſuites a temper that neither <hi>fears God,</hi> nor <hi>loves man.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:152860:16"/>
               <head>For Concluſion</head>
               <p>'TIs not poſſible ſo to acquit my ſelf of <hi>every</hi> Objection, as to leave all men ſatisfied, eſpecially ſuch as carry a <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſe</hi> of preferment, profit, or faction; Men that have in deſign <hi>exorbitancies</hi> of power or wealth, will hardly with arguments be reclaim'd; and ſome have I known that have ſo long poſſeſt their heads with <hi>ſtrong notions,</hi> that they are not capable to take in <hi>Reaſon</hi> againſt them, and thereupon run on frantick in error till there be a <hi>Rotation</hi> in their brains; ſuch there are that with confidence ſo often have told a lie, that at length themſelves believe it to be <hi>truth;</hi> but with reſpect to the ſtate of our affairs, we are not in a poſture to reſent the intereſt or wilfulneſſe of a <hi>few,</hi> but the ſafety of the <hi>major part;</hi> let not the greedineſſe or ambition of <hi>ſome,</hi> hazard a deſtruction to <hi>all.</hi> It may ſuffice that the <hi>main</hi> obſtructors are the <hi>very</hi> perſons that have moſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd themſelves; If they retain <hi>double,</hi> to what they were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of, 'tis much better, then with the <hi>generality,</hi> who would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the quiet enjoyment of their <hi>own;</hi> where <hi>one</hi> has been improv'd by the times, <hi>one hundred</hi> have been impoveriſh'd: For be it known, that ſuch as have been eminently active, and ſweld in power and purchaſes are in number <hi>few</hi> in compariſon with the <hi>multitude,</hi> that have been either miſled, driven on, or not engag'd; Nay I may aver, that even upon this quarrel the ſpirit of the people has been ſo tir'd, that upon a juſt compute there is ſcarce <hi>one</hi> to <hi>one hundred</hi> againſt a Cloſure.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Now then, Suppoſe we, all <hi>compoſition</hi> with the King de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry'd; Suppoſe we him in <hi>armes,</hi> bickt with a forraign force.</item>
                  <item>Suppoſe in <hi>Ireland, Scotland:</hi> Nay, with <hi>us,</hi> there are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtions upon that account.</item>
                  <item>Suppoſe upon termes of power we are aw'd to receive our Prince.</item>
                  <item>Suppoſe the <hi>many</hi> for the ſake of peace deliver up the <hi>few</hi> as a <hi>ſacrifice</hi> to the injur'd, and to <hi>eaſe</hi> the Publick. <hi>What then?</hi>—I have done.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:152860:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
